A Guide to the J. Louis von der Mehden Papers 1979.0019
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
J. Louis von der Mehden Papers
undated, 1894-1955
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1979.0019
10.5 Linear Feet
J. Louis von der Mehden, Jr. was born 20 July 1873 in San Francisco, California. Von der Mehden held several positions in San Francisco before moving east to New York City after the 1906 earthquake. He was steadily employed as a cellist or conductor with theatrical or commercial bands. Von der Mehden worked for a year as the musical director of Herald Square Theater before becoming involved full time in the recording industry, working at different times for five different phonograph studios: U.S. Phonograph, Pathé Frère, Columbia, Lyraphone and the Victor Talking Machine Company. On some recordings he played cello in the orchestra; more regularly he would conduct performances, often arranging the music the night before the recording sessions. In 1926, the von der Mehden's moved to Old Saybrook, Connecticut, full-time, having purchased a house in 1911. J. Louis von der Mehden, Jr. died 27 August 1954 in Middlesex Memorial Hospital and was buried in Cypress Cemetery at Saybrook Point.
Biography
J. Louis von der Mehden, Jr. was born 20 July 1873 in San Francisco, California. He entered the Royal Conservatory at Leipzig, Germany, on 21 April 1892 and graduated in 1894, having studied music theory and composition, piano and cello. He had no formal high school education, and in 1915 began a high school equivalency correspondence course through the University of Chicago, which he completed in 1922. In June 1922, Oskaloosa College in Iowa conferred on him an honorary Doctor of Music Degree. He began studying music composition and history at Yale University in October 1922 and received a Bachelor of Music degree in 1924. In November 1923, he began correspondence courses at the Chicago School of Law and earned his law degree in 1927.
J. Louis von der Mehden married Susan Evelyn Bates (1874-1955) 26 March 1899 in Palo Alto, California. Susan graduated from the San José State Normal School. In later years she gave French and music lessons and also tried to publish children's verse. In 1908, Louis composed several series of Musical Pictures for the Young, piano pieces that were preceded by one of Susan's poems, and in 1909 they worked together in the creation of several sets of children's verses called Little Bagatelles.
Before the 1906 earthquake, the von der Mehdens lived in San Francisco, where Louis led band concerts at the Presidio. He was first cellist in a San Francisco orchestra for eight years, under the direction of Fritz Scheel and one year under the direction of Henry Holmes. After the earthquake, the von der Mehdens moved to New York City. Louis was steadily employed as a cellist or conductor with theatrical or commercial bands. Every year, from 1907 through 1912, von der Mehden conducted a small orchestra during business hours between Thanksgiving and Christmas at Hearn's Department Store. For several years, he played cello in Ahren's People's Symphony, a series of low- admission educational musical programs given in Carnegie Hall. In November 1908, he went to Cleveland on a one week tour with the Russian Symphony Orchestra.
Von der Mehden's early compositions were published by Carl Fischer, Inc. of New York. Several of his compositions were reviewed in the February and April 1909 issues of Musical Observer. In addition to composing, von der Mehden arranged and orchestrated music of other composers, which was also published by Fisher. Arranging and orchestrating constituted the major part of his work at Fisher after 1910, although several of his own pieces were published that year. In 1911, he began arranging and orchestrating music for the New York office of the Italian publishing house, Ricordi.
On 8 November 1910, von der Mehden was elected musical director of the Herald Square Theater, where he was conducting operettas. He had several labor disputes during his experience as operetta conductor and a quarrel with the manager of the Theater on 26 May 1911 prompted him to give up his position and move with his orchestra to the Winter Garden [a Schubert Theater]. An incident on 5 July 1911 resulted in his resignation from this position as well as his resignation from the musician's union.
Between 1912 and 1918, von der Mehden had virtually a full-time career in the recording industry, working at different times for five different phonograph studios: U.S. Phonograph, Pathé Frère, Columbia, Lyraphone and the Victor Talking Machine Company. On some recordings he played cello in the orchestra; more regularly, he would conduct performances, often arranging the music the night before the recording session. He also had some of his own compositions recorded.
As an arranger for Ricordi, von der Mehden was brought into close contact with James Reese Europe in 1915-1916. Europe was the creator of the foxtrot and was a very important transitional figure in the pre-history of jazz on the East Coast. Von der Mehden arranged and orchestrated some of Europe's music at Ricordi, often taking the music from dictation. Also in 1915, von der Mehden played cello in the production of George M. Cohan's Hello, Broadway! At this time, von der Mehden returned to the traditional European models in his compositions, giving up efforts to incorporate the current trends in popular music. Most of the works written in 1915 were composed specifically to be recorded.
In 1911, the von der Mehdens had purchased property in Old Saybrook, Connecticut, where they built a house. Until 1926, they retained both an apartment in New York City, where Susan was a representative at a toy manufacturing company, and the house in Connecticut. Susan's position was terminated in 1925 and they moved permanently to Old Saybrook. The couple spent a great deal of time working in their garden, which eventually became their major activity and a source of pride. From this time until his death, von der Mehden gave piano lessons to one or two students a year. He no longer composed steadily, and he spent considerable time practicing the piano, having given up the cello.
During the 1920s, von der Mehden was active in the local Republican party, and served for a while as special constable. He was a thirty-second degree mason and was awarded a medal in 1954, commemorating his fifty years of membership in the San Francisco lodge.
J. Louis von der Mehden, Jr. died 27 August 1954, in Middlesex Memorial Hospital and was buried in Cypress Cemetery at Saybrook Point. Susan von der Mehden died on 20 June 1955.
[Biographical information provided by the contents of the collection and James P. Pareakilas, "The Life and Works of J. Louis von der Mehden, Jr., 1873-1954" (M.A. thesis, University of Connecticut, 1974.]
Scope and Content
The papers document the activities of the von der Mehdens from the period of 1908 through 1955. The collection contains diaries, newspaper clippings, correspondence, notes, financial records, photographs, musical manuscripts, scores, publications, and celluloid cylinders.
The entries in the diaries detail daily occurrences with few r eflective comments or notations. A large number of newspaper clippings are fastened to the pages, especially on birthday and wedding anniversaries in the later years. Also included are three dietary diaries kept by Susan von der Mehden between 1923 and 1925.
The second series contains loose materials removed from the diaries: correspondence (primarily 1953-1955), including letters of consolation following the death of J. Louis von der Mehden; notes (1909-1954); financial papers and newspaper clippings (1912- 1955), which include stock information and receipts; and biographical materials, including newspaper clippings of his fifty year membership in the Masons, of relatives and friends, and of his death. Also found in this series are ten photographs of Louis and Susan von der Mehden, von der Mehden's diplomas, and an unidentified scrapbook.
The musical compositions include manuscripts for fifteen works, including symphonies, concertos, quartets, and sonatas written between 1909 and 1924. Except for two of the orchestral works, Achilles and Concerto for Piano and Orchestra, there is a piano score in addition to the orchestral score. There are also sketches of several smaller works of which there is no final copy. There is also a waltz entitled Our Golden Anniversary Waltz, written for his fiftieth anniversary in 1949.
The bequest of Susan von der Mehden included three conditions: First, the music was to be made available to students and to be performed if possible; Second, a storage area for the music was to be provided; and Third, the unpublished compositions of J. Louis von der Mehden, Jr. were to be printed by the University. The compositions were published in a facsimile edition by University Publications and were distributed across the country. The six volumes and supplement include two male quartets, two volumes of piano pieces, a march song for solo and chorus, and an intermezzo for piano.
The wax cylinders found in the collection are from von der Mehden's own music collection. Eighteen cylinders are recordings of works either composed by or conducted by von der Mehden. The remaining eighty-six cylinders contain works composed and conducted by others as well as six vaudeville sketches. The identification of the cylinders [Box 18] is questionable because the lids had been separated from the boxes at some point.
In addition to the papers, Mrs. Von der Mehden bequeathed to the University $500,000, with the understanding that the funds would support the construction of a recital hall in memory of her husband.
Organization
Series I: Diaries (1908-1954) consists of forty-nine diaries written by J. Louis and Susan von der Mehden, Jr. The diaries are arranged chronologically by author.
Series II: Personal Papers (undated, 1909-1955) consists of loose material removed from the diaries and are arranged alphabetically.
Series III: Music Manuscripts (1894-1949) contains hand written manuscripts of fifteen major works and are arranged chronologically by date of composition.
Series IV: Published Works (undated, 1906-1915) consists of individual works which were published during the composer's life time, as well as a facsimile of his collected works printed posthumously by the University of Connecticut. The series is arranged chronologically.
Series V: Wax Cylinders (undated) contains the wax cylinders owned by von der Mehden.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
US Everlasting 1979-0019.cd1
Arrangement
The materials are arranged by format.
Acquisition Information
The J. Louis von der Mehden, Jr. Papers were bequeathed to the University of Connecticut by his widow. The collection was originally housed in the Music Library and was transferred to Special Collections [now Archives & Special Collections]in 1975. The photocopies of von der Mehden's 1915 musical arrangements were donated in 2006.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Manuscripts (document genre); Financial Records; Old Saybrook (inhabited place); Diaries; Notes; Scores; New York (inhabited place); United States (nation); Photographs; Publications (documents); Correspondence; Secret societies; Concertos; Quartets; Sonatas; Symphonies; Sound recordings; Violin and cello music; Vaudeville
- Series I: Diaries, 1908-1954
  - Diaries (15 v.), 1908-1922 (Box 1)
  - Diaries (10 v.), 1923-1932 (Box 2)
  - Diaries (7 v.), 1933-1934, 1936-1940 (Box 3)
  - Diaries (4 v.), 1941-1944 (Box 4)
  - Diaries (4 v.), 1945-1948 (Box 5)
  - Diaries (3 v.), 1949-1951 (Box 6)
  - Diaries (3 v.), 1952-1954 (Box 7)
  - Dietary diaries (3 v.), 1923-1925 (Box 7)
- Series II: Personal Papers, 1894-1955
  - Correspondence, 1925, 1931, 1936, 1953-1955 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Diplomas
    - Royal Conservatory at Leipzig, 1894 (Box OS)
    - Yale University, 1924 (Box OS)
    - Chicago School of Law, 1927 (Box OS)
  - Notes, 1909-1954 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Financial Records, 1912-1955 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Financial newspaper clippings, 1933-1954 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Biographical material, 1946-1954 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Printed material, 1921, 1926, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Photographs
    - Susan E. (Bates) von der Mehden (4), [1905-1913] (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - J. Louis and Susan von der Mehden (2), [1915-1920] (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
    - J. Louis von der Mehden, Jr. (2), [190-?] (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook, [1906-1920] (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Series III: Music Manuscripts, 1894-1949
  - "Pilgrim" Symphony, orchestral score, 1909 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - "Pilgrim" Symphony, piano solo, 1909 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Achilles Symphony, orchestral score and outline of symphony, 1909 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Sketches of unidentified pieces, 1917-1919 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Ye Merry Christmas Bells, sketch, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - 24 Preludes and Fugues for Piano, 1920 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Quartette No. 1, "Motive," individual parts (2 sets), 1921 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Quartette No. 1, "Motive," score, 1921 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - March Americana, piano score, 1921 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - March Americana, orchestral score, 1921 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Symphony No. 2, "Orpheus," piano score, 1921 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Symphony No. 2, "Orpheus," piano score, 1921 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - American Rhapsody, No. 1, piano score, 1921 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - American Rhapsody, No. 1, orchestral score, 1922 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Sonata No. 1 for violin and piano, 1922 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Symphony No. 3, "Yale," piano score, 1922 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Symphony No. 3, "Yale," orchestral score, 1923 (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - Paul Revere's Ride, Symphonic poem, piano and orchestral scores, 1923 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Quintet No. 1 for piano, two violins, viola, violoncello; individual parts, 1923 (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - Trio No. 1 for violin, violoncello and piano; individual parts, 1923 (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - Halcyone, Symphonic poem, piano and orchestral scores, 1923 (Box 11, Folder 32)
  - Quartet No. 1, "Cycle" for violin, viola, violoncello, and piano; individual parts, 1923 (Box 11, Folder 33)
  - Concerto for piano and orchestra, piano solo, 1924 (Box 11, Folder 34)
  - Book of chorales, fugues [?], 1894 (Box 11, Folder 35)
  - Unidentified segment of a composition, undated (Box 11, Folder 36)
- Series IV: Published Works, 1906-1915
  - Flora, 1906 (Box 12, Folder 37)
  - Triumphant America, 1906 (Box 12, Folder 38)
  - Twelve Pieces for Pianoforte, Volume I, 1906 (Box 12, Folder 39)
  - Twelve Pieces for Pianoforte, Volume II, 1906 (Box 12, Folder 40)
  - Bubbles, male quartet, 1909 (Box 12, Folder 41)
  - Christmas Light, Behold!, 1913 (Box 12, Folder 42)
  - Collected Works of J. Louis von der Mehden, Jr., undated
    - Collected Works of J. Louis von der Mehden, Jr. (Box 12, Folder 43)
    - Volume II, supplement (Box 12, Folder 44)
    - Volume IV (Box 12, Folder 45)
    - Volume VI (Box 12, Folder 46)
  - Musical Arrangements (photocopies), 1915 (Box 12, Folder 47)
    Scope and Contents
    [Rouge et Noir Walk, Helter-Skelter (1 p.), Shy and Sly Trot, Hi! There! One Step, The Castle Doggy-Fox Trot, Monkey-Doodle Cake Walk, Queen Louise Valse.]
- Series V: Wax Cylinders, undated
  General note
  [Note: length, in minutes, of cylinders indicated in parentheses after title]
  - Von der Mehden and his Orchestra
    - Baby Polka, (2) No. 421 (Box 18)
    - Simplicius Waltz (Danube Maidens), (4) No. 1406 (Box 13)
    - Air by Bach, (4) No. 1443 (Box 13)
    - Whispering Flowers Characteristic, (4) No. 1490 (Box 13)
    - The Butterfly. Morceau Characteristic (Solo for Flute and Clarinet), (4) No. 1620 (Box 13)
  - U.S. Concert Band under the direction of von der Mehden
    - The Demon (March), (2) No. 485 (Box 13)
    - Awakening of the Lion, (4) No. 1507 (Box 18)
    - Lustspiel Overture, (4) No. 1508 (Box 13)
    - Ever or Never Waltz, (4) No. 1509 (Box 13)
    - La Serenade and March Carmen (Valse Espagnole), (4) No. 1510 (Box 13)
  - Von der Mehden and Orchestra
    - Hungarian Dance No. 1, (2) No. 476 (Box 13)
    - Norwegian Dance No. 2, (2) No. 507 (Box 13)
    - Tancredi Overture, (4) No. 1475 (Box 13)
    - Violets-Waltz, (4) No. 1476 (Box 13)
  - Band under the direction of von der Mehden
    - The Mill in the Forest. Idyll, (4) No. 1388 (Box 13)
    - Selections from "Robin Hood", (4) No. 1416 (Box 13)
    - Manhattan Beach March and the Gladiator March, (4) No. 1421 (Box 13)
    - Call of America, J. Louis von der Mehden, Jr., (2) No. 477 (Box 13)
  - U.S. Military Band
    - Tenth Regiment March, (2) No. 450 (Box 14)
    - United Empire March, (2) No. 440 (Box 14)
    - Orange Music No. 1, (2) No. 496 (Box 14)
    - Orange Music No. 2, (2) No. 497 (Box 14)
    - Foolish Sammy. Medley March, (2) No. 499 (Box 18)
    - Fete Boheme from Scenes Pittoresque, (4) No. 1477 (Box 15)
    - The Scarf Dance from Ballet "Callirhoe", (4) No. 1480 (Box 15)
  - emph render="bold">U.S. Concert Band
    - Sounds from England, (4) No. 1593 (Box 18)
    - Grand Selections of Scotch Melodies, (4) No. 1604 (Box 16)
    - Laurentian Echoes, (4) No. 1614 (Box 18)
    - The Rye Waltzes, (4) No. 1615 (Box 18)
    - Germany I Welcome Thee, (4) No. 1616 (Box 17)
  - Band
    - Merry Wives of Windsor. Overture, (4) No. 1491 (Box 15)
    - Czardas from Ballet "Coppelia", 4) No. 1492 (Box 15)
  - Metropolitan Opera House Chorus
    - La Zingarella. Anvil Chorus from Il Trovatore, (4) No. 21137 (Box 17)
    - Coro Dei Mattadori. From Traviata, (4) No. 21140 (Box 17)
    - Vieni O Guerriero. From Aida, (4) No. 21141 (Box 17)
    - Bridal Chorus from Lohengrin, (4) No. 21257 (Box 17)
    - Pilgrim Chorus. From Tannhauser, (4) No. 21258 (Box 17)
    - Deposons Les Armes. Soldiers Chorus from Faust, (4) No. 21374 (Box 17)
  - Peerless Quartette with Orchestral Accompaniment
    - March of the Men of Harlech, (4) No. 1486 (Box 18)
    - That Raggedy Rag, (4) No. 1517 (Box 15)
    - I Surrender All, (4) No. 1552 (Box 16)
  - H.L. Spitalny, Violinist
    - Legende, (4) No. 1573 (Box 16)
    - Serenade, (4) No. 1574 (Box 16)
    - The Swan. The Bee., (4) No. 1575 (Box 16)
    - Preislied. From Meistersinger, (4) No. 1576 (Box 16)
  - I. Piroschnikoff, Concertina soloist with piano accompaniment
    - Kuyawiak. Second Mazourka, (4) No. 1592 (Box 16)
    - Grand Valse, (4) No. 1617 (Box 17)
  - Dr. Al Popper, Violinist with Mrs. Popper, piano accompaniment
    - Boka Ksergoie. Rapsodie Hongroise, (4) No. 1456 (Box 14)
    - Gavotte, (4) No. 1465 (Box 14)
  - Florentine Trio
    - Marie. Nocturne, (4) No. 1521 (Box 15)
    - To a Wild Rose, (4) No. 1528 (Box 16)
  - Florentine Quintette
    - Idilio, (2) No. 501 (Box 14)
    - Celebrated Menuett and Fairy Tales, (4) No. 1307 (Box 14)
    - Humoreske, (4) No. 1434 (Box 14)
    - Gondoliers and Venetian Love Song from "A Day in Venice", (4) No. 1523 (Box 15)
  - H.H. McClaskey
    - The Day is Ended, (4) No. 1405 (Box 14)
    - One Heart Divine, (4) No. 1407 (Box 14)
    - The Homeland (with Edmund A. Jahn), (4) No. 1487 (Box 15)
    - Scots, Wha Hae Wi' Wallace Bled, (4) No. 1563 (Box 17)
  - Elsie Baker
    - Cradle Song, (4) No. 1469 (Box 15)
    - Pickaninny's Lullaby, (4) No. 1499 (Box 15)
  - Will Oakland
    - Sweet Genevieve (with William H. Thompson), (4) No. 1484 (Box 15)
    - My Sweetheart's the Man in the Moon (with William H. Thompson), (4) No. 1485 (Box 15)
    - With All Her Faults I Love Her Still, (4) No. 1446 (Box 14)
    - The Lass from County Mayo, (4) No. 1532 (Box 16)
  - George W. Ballard & William H. Thompson
    - When the Old Oaken Bucket Was New, (4) No. 1547 (Box 16)
  - Fred Van Eps, Banjo & Albert Benzler, Piano
    - Campin' on de Old Suwanee, (2) No. 467 (Box 14)
    - Silver Heels, March-Two-Step, (2) No. 468 (Box 17)
  - John Barnes Wells
    - If I Were You; The Elf Man; The Dearest Place, (4) No. 1481 (Box 15)
    - Boat Song; To Lucasta, (4) No. 1511 (Box 15)
  - Collins and Harlan
    - Ragtime Soldier Man, (2) No. 510 (Box 17)
    - That Slippery Slide Trombone, (4) No. 1525 (Box 16)
    - Buddy Boy, (4) No. 1580 (Box 16)
  - Others
    - Do You Remember the Last Waltz?, Henry Burr, (4) No. 1500 (Box 15)
    - Take Me Back to the Garden of Love, Henry Burr and Chorus with Orchestral accompaniment, (4) No. 1518 (Box 15)
    - Capitol City March-Two Step, (Xylophone Solo). Albert Benzler with Orchestral accompaniment, (2) No. 481 (Box 14)
    - Return to the Fields, (Polka). Albert Benzler with Orchestral accompaniment, (2) No. 491 (Box 14)
    - Ay do mi! El Rey que Rabio, Mame de la Roche, (4) No. 21804 (Box 17)
    - Carmen Il Est Temps encore, ----- & Erard, (4) No. 35015 (Box 17)
    - Ainsi Qu'on Voil des Bles, Borschneck & Erard,(4) No. 35016 (Box 17)
    - Seguidille et Duo (Carmen), (4) No. 35017 (Box 17)
    - N'est se plus ma Main (Manon), Henis & Erard, (4) No. 35019 (Box 17)
    - Ave Marie (Intermezzo from Cavalleri Rusticana),(4) No. 1461 (Box 14)
    - Scenes that are Brightest (Maritana),(4) No. 1555 (Box 16)
    - Brown October Ale (Robin Hood),(4) No. 1564 (Box 16)
    - Soldier's Farewell Primier Mixed Quartet, (4) No. 1625 (Box 17)
    - Visions of Sunny Italy, William Edward Foster, (4) No. 1618 (Box 17)
    - Hosanna, Frank Croxton,(4) No. 1447 (Box 14)
    - When it Rains, Sweetheart, Manuel Romain,(4) No. 1549 (Box 16)
    - Flora's Holiday, Frank Croxton Quartette,(4) No. 1562 (Box 16)
    - Bendemeer's Stream, Albert A. Wiederhold,(4) No. 1468 (Box 15)
    - Ancient Court Whisperings, Gavotte. Bells Solo. Albert Benzler with orchestral accompaniment,(4) No. 1506 (Box 15)
    - When I'm Big I'll Be a Soldier, Lilian Homesley,(4) No. 1554 (Box 16)
    - Facilita. Air with Variations, Bohumir Kryl, soloist with Band accompaniment, (4) No. 1306 (Box 14)
    - Darkies Jubilee, Fred Van Eps with Orchestral accompaniment, (4) No. 1512 (Box 15)
    - Fafang Onskan (Swedish), Arvid Asplund,(4) No. 21578 (Box 17)
    - Cantilena(from First Cello Concerto), Louis Heine with orchestral accompaniment,(4) No. 1503 (Box 15)
    - Take Me Back to Babyland, Lilian Homesley, (4) No. 1467 (Box 14)
  - Vaudeville Sketches
    - Uncle Josh and the Osteopath, (Cal Stewart), (4) No. 1350 (Box 14)
    - In Jaytown, (Steven Porter, Byron G. Harlan), (4) No. 1488 (Box 18)
    - Shipmates, (4) No. 1539 (Box 16)
    - Matrimonial Troubles, (4) No. 1541 (Box 16)
    - Uncle Josh's New Year's Pledge, (Cal Stewart) (4) No. 1598 (Box 16)
    - Uncle Josh and the Insurance Agent, (Cal Stewart) (4) No. 1640 (Box 17)